I'm Beau Timken, master sake sommelier.
About six years ago, when I opened my store, True Sake, I had to develop; it's a store that's dedicated to selling sake, I had to develop a system that would allow people, or kind of disarm them, to describe what kind of sakes they like.
And the best way to do that is I would speak to their; I would have them speak to their beer and wine profiles.
And basically, everybody is comfortable talking to what they like in a wine and a beer, and then what we can do is we can overlap that into different styles and categories of sake.
Now Ginjo, in specif, specifically is geared towards people who like lighter, softer, cleaner wines. Now, taste match is a system that if if you like a big Sauvignon Blanc, a big dirty Zinfandel, and you like big Belgian's or big stouts, you generally aren't going to like the same sake maybe as somebody who likes a Sauvignon Blanc and a Kiran beer.
Those are cleaner, lighter, compact flavors.
Well, guess what?
In the sake world, the cleaner, lighter flavors are in sort of the Ginjo category, and what I'll recommend; when people come in, they say, well, I kind of like a lighter white wine; I'd like a, like a Sauvignon Blanc, I like not a super oaky Chardonnay; it's got some body to it; I like ales; kind of clean beers.
Then Ginjo is definitely kind of your zone.
You can definitely achieve those flavors and those textures and those components in that category.
So, we're using the taste match system.
If you feel like you want something where you would have a food that you would throw a white wine at, specifically like a Sauvignon Blanc, something like seafood or shellfish, same thing goes with Ginjo sake.
So again, if you want to think in terms of light, clean, compact, aromatic; if you like that in your wines; white; I'm not talking about big, beefy reds, and I'm not talking about super fruity wines either; kind of the neutral in between wines.
That is the same category overlap that you would have with Ginjo style sake.